so now let's look at cycle three in
cycle three we will try to issue the
next instruction which is this
multiplication we will look at whether
we have a unit yes we do
it's gonna be a multiply instruction f2
and f4 r LD 2 and the actual value of f4
so here we will mark the actual value of
F 4 this is our second operand as 2.5
because that's what this says and then
for the first operand we will mark that
we are waiting for LD 2 this is gonna
make it very easy to determine which
things are ready to execute because the
instructions should not really have
anything here if it's ready to execute
and this instruction is not gonna be
ready yet because it's waiting for the
second load and then we're gonna rename
f0 so that it points to the reservation
station in this case ml 1 that contains
this instruction in this third cycle the
first load is still executing now the
question is can the second load begin
execution if we have a pipeline load
story on it then yes it would be because
in the previous cycle we have begun this
instruction it's in the second stage now
so now we can begin the first stage for
this instruction but let's say that we
don't have a pipeline load store unit
that only our ad unit is pipeline in
which case this load will not be able to
dispatch into the execution unit until
cycle 4 because basically the execution
unit will be occupied in cycles 2 & 3 by
the first load so we will kind of mark
that in cycle 4 we will be able to begin
execution of this if everything else is
ready and nothing is still broadcast in
the result the first load is still
executing in cycle 3 so now we go to
cycle 4 in cycle 4 we will try to issue
the next instruction which is this
subtract it's going to use an adder unit
so this is just to mark it as a subtract
we're gonna issue it in this cycle f2 +
f6 rld 2 + LD 1 so this one actually is
waiting like this and we also have to
mark the f8 as renamed to ad 1 so this
completes the issuing in this cycle now
let's see
if we can dispatch something well this
is psycho for in psychos 2 & 3 the first
load has been executing now it's ready
to write so basically we can begin
execution of this instruction so it's
been dispatched in cycle 4 now we no
longer need this are any of the other
instructions ready to execute well not
in this cycle so now we're gonna write
the result in LD 1 LD 1 here we kind of
note it here that is going to write the
result in cycle 4 which is now so now
we're gonna write to the result of this
instruction so we can mark here that we
are writing that result and what's going
to happen now is basically it's gonna
broadcast with a tag of LD 1 and the
value will load it from memory from this
address and that value is going to be
put to f6 so what we do now is we're
gonna broadcast that value and capture
that value everywhere where we have LD 1
in this table so each of these is gonna
compare its tag to LD 1 and wherever we
see an LD 1 we're gonna get that value
so in this case only this particular
instruction is gonna latch that value so
let's say that the value is 7.1 okay
that completes the result capture we
still have to put 7.1 in the actual
register f6 so somewhere in f6 we have
7.1 now because this was pointing to lb
1 LD 1 is done now so now we can find
that value in the register file and now
we can free this reservation station so
when you free reservation stations what
you really do is you just turn off the
valid bit for the entry you don't really
have to erase the whole entry so I'm
gonna erase it just to prepare for the
next instruction but keep in mind that
in real Hardware there is just a single
bit that just gets marked to 0 and that
is considered to free the reservation
station now in this cycle in cycle 4 we
have issued an instruction we have tried
to dispatch an instruction and we found
that only the load really can be
dispatched and we have written a our
result back only what result can be
written per cycle anyway so that's it
for this cycle so let's move on to cycle